A Guide to the Carneal and Johnston Architectural Drawings, 1939-1968, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Carneal and Johnston Architectural Drawings, 1939-1968, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-008
3.0 cu. ft. 3 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Carneal and Johnston Architectural Drawings were transferred from the Office of the University Architect in February 2001.
Biographical/Historical Note
J. Ambler Johnston was born in 1885 and was a 1904 graduate of Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute. He also earned a master of science degree in 1905 from VPI. Johnston resided in Richmond, Virginia, where he served as a charter member of the Richmond Rotary Club and was a Civil War scholar. He died in 1974.
William Leigh Carneal, Jr., was born in Richmond on October 24, 1881, and graduated in 1903 from the Virginia Military Institute. He began his architectural practice around 1906 following a three year stint as a clerk in his father's company, Sitterding-Carneal-Davis Company. He died in 1958.
In 1908, Carneal and Johnston combined offices. The firm's first building was the original McBryde Hall on the VPI campus, completed in 1917. The firm helped to incorporate the Collegiate Gothic style to the campus landscape. For a brief period, the firm included a third partner and was known as Carneal, Johnston, & Wright. Both Carneal and Johnston retired in the 1950s. In 1999, the surviving firm of Carneal and Johnston merged with Ballou, Justice, & Upton Architects.
Scope and Content
The collection contains detail drawings, sketches, and tracings of several campus buildings. Items include 1939 drawings of Agricultural Hall, 1952 and 1959 drawings of the Academic Science building, 1959 and 1961 drawings of the Engineering building, and 1961 and 1968 sketches of dorm buildings. The collection also contains tracings of the Biology, Geo (Geology?), and Education buildings.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Bio, Geo, Education Building T.A.C. original tracings; drawings. (Box 1)
- Dorm 1 and 2: Detail sketches, 1961. (Box 2)
- New Dorm 1 and 2: Niche Sketches, 1961. (Box 2)
- Dorm 9: Detail sketches, 1968. (Box 2)
- Engineering Building: First Addition, Detail Drawings, December 5, 1959. (Box 2)
- Academic Science Building: Detail Drawings, 1952. (Box 2)
- Science Building: Detail Drawings, 1959. (Box 3)
- Agricultural Hall Detail Drawings, April 18 & April 27, 1939. (Box 3)
- Engineering Building: Addition, Detail Drawings, April 28, 1961. (Box 3)
- Dorm 2 and Barracks 3: Sketches. (Folder 1)